This is the Introduction to
the Still Technique lecture.
During this lecture,
we're going to
discuss the history of
the Still Technique,
we'll talk about the
principles and the
physiologic mechanisms
of the technique,
we'll go over the indications
and contraindications
of the Still
Technique, and explain
how to apply the
principles of the Still
Technique to any given
somatic dysfunction.
The Still technique
was developed or
rediscovered by Dr.
Richard Van Buskirk, D.O.
It's important to note
that Dr. Still really
didn't teach techniques,
so his students
had to learn from
listening to how he applied
his principles or
watching what he did.
Dr. Van Buskirk based the
technique of the Still
technique on the writings
of Dr. Charles Hazard as
well as descriptions of
techniques by, from Dr.
Carl Philip McConnell
and Dr. Herb Yates. Dr.
Yates described the method
as indirect and direct.
So Dr. Van Buskirk really,
he used some writings
and then he was in
contact with people who
learned from people who
learned from Dr. Still.
The still technique is
basically a passive technique
which utilizes indirect
and then direct motions
and it is most likely
to use the physiologic
principles of the muscle
spindle and also articulation.
This will address the
muscular myofascial component
and the joint component
of the dysfunction.
As you recall,
the muscle spindle reflex,
the theory behind it is that
by compressing muscles past
their neutral position,
this can result in a quieting
of the gamma motor gain
to the muscle spindle, which
leads to a resetting of
the tension and hypertonicity
of the muscle fibers.
The articulatory
portion of the technique
basically brings the
dysfunction through its barrier,
so you're working at
the joint level here.
This slide describes the basic
principles of the
STIL technique.
So first you want to
evaluate the affected tissue
and then place it into
its position of ease.
Next you're going to
introduce a force vector to
the affected tissue from
another part of the body.
So if you're treating
the cervical spine, you
may be putting your hand
on the top of the head and
compressing down to the
region of the cervical
spine that you're treating.
If you're treating the
thoracic spine, for instance,
you may be using the
shoulders to add a
compression to that region.
So you're going to add a
gentle compression, which
should be less than two
pounds or one kilogram.
Then using that compression
as your starting
point, you're going
to move the affected
tissue into its freedom
a little bit more.
and then bring it the other
direction through the barriers.
As you do this, you
may feel a little bump
or you may feel a
click or you may hear
a click, but that
doesn't always happen.
Finally, you're
going to passively
move the area you're
treating back to
a neutral position
and then reassess.
What are the contraindications
for the still
technique? Well, any
condition where somatic
dysfunction is involved
is an indication.
Contraindications for
the STIL technique are
similar to other
techniques we've discussed.
If the patient can't
tolerate a treatment
position, that's a
contraindication. You may
need to modify the
technique or use a different
technique depending
on what you're doing.
If there's radicular
pain when performing
something to the
cervical spine using
compression, like when
you're doing a Sperling
maneuver, that would
be contraindicated.
What can you do? You
can try to reposition
or try doing the technique with
traction or just do a
different technique.
Similarly,
any condition of a region
being treated where
introducing traction or
compression is contraindicated
would be a contraindication
for this technique.
Somebody had a hip
replacement, you have to be
careful. the positioning
sometimes if the
technique requires you
to flex the hip up to a
certain pass a certain
point that might be a
contraindication if somebody
has shoulder pathology
you might not be able
to do certain treatments
with the shoulder
or certain first rib
techniques because you're
involving the shoulder
so any any treatment that
moves or puts force into
the shoulder if the person
had a chronic shoulder
dislocation or separation
would be contraindicated
any recent trauma fracture
or dislocation at the
area being treated would
be a contraindication for
the still technique you
also need to use caution
in patients with
osteoporosis or malignancy
rheumatologic disorders
congenital malformations stenosis
and other clinical diseases
you have to use your
clinical judgment side
effects of the still technique
are similar to other
osteopathic techniques.
They're pretty much
transient. You may get
some fatigue, some
soreness or some stiffness
and this is primarily
due to restoration
of circulation to areas
that were previously
dysfunctional and
there's been a
release of muscular
waste products.
Typically after you treat
anyone with any type
of OMT you tell them they
may feel a little sore
and ask them to stay
hydrated because that's
going to help with the
transient side effects.
Let's go over a case now
just to see how the still
technique can be used in
a case setting. So a 50
-year-old female physician
presents to your office
complaining that she
twisted her back wrong while
treating a rather large
patient with a muscle energy
technique. She's having a
constant sharp pain in the
right lower back which
is exacerbated with left
rotation and deep breathing
nothing makes it better
the pain is non-radiating she
has no associated numbness
tingling or weakness or
bowel and bladder function
changes she had an x-ray
of her lumbar sacral spine
done yesterday and it
was normal she has a past
medical history of reinaud's
disease she's had two
cesarean sections denies
alcohol, drugs, or tobacco use.
Her parents both have
hypertension, and she
has five siblings who
are alive and well.
The only positive in
the review of systems
is the back pain.
Everything else is normal.
On physical exam,
her lower extremity
motor is 5 out
of 5 bilaterally.
L4 and S1 reflexes are
2 out of 4 bilaterally.
There's no gross sensory
deficit in the lower
extremities. There's
negative straight
leg raise bilaterally,
and there's negative
costovertebral angle
tenderness bilaterally.
The Faber test is
negative bilaterally.
Bilaterally, she has
paravertebral muscle
spasms right greater
than left. She has a
right psoas spasm,
bilateral hamstring spasm.
L1 is found to have
a dysfunction of FRS
right, and the left
piriformis is hypertonic
with an associated
counterstrain point.
So, it looks like this
patient has low back
pain, muscle spasm, and
somatic dysfunction in the
lumbar, sacrum, and
lower extremity regions.
Well what do we want
to do? For the low back
pain we're going to
prescribe some hamstrings,
psoas, paraspinal
muscle stretches,
also a pure form of stretch.
I typically like to have
the patients stretch twice
a day and we'll tell them
to do each stretch. For
instance maybe stretch the
hamstrings 20 seconds relax
for a few seconds stretch it
again for 20 seconds relax
stretch it a third time
for about a minute's worth
of stretching total and
then switch and do the other
leg and do that twice a
day so i would explain that
she should be doing that
for all those muscles there
for her muscle spasm the
stretch is as above uh somatic
dysfunction for lumbar
spine, we're going to do some
OMT, maybe do some soft
tissue and still technique.
For the sacrum, which
is the piriformis,
we're going to do
some counter strain.
And for the lower extremity,
we'll do some muscle energy
for those hamstrings.
And also for the
psoas, you could
do some muscle energy as well.
Now you're probably
wondering, how do we treat
L1 FRS right with the
still technique. Well,
basically, we would have
the patient sitting up.
We would come around, and
you're going to see this
in the lab, but we're
going to come around and
have our axilla on one
shoulder and the hand of
the same arm on the other
shoulder, and we're going
to basically guide the
lumbar spine into flexion,
rotation right, and
sideburn right. Then we're
going to add a little bit
of compression down to
the L1 region, maintain
that compression, and
maybe bring it slightly
more into the freedom, but
then you're going to take
it through the barrier.
And once you take it
through the barrier, you're
going to bring the patient
back to a regular seated
position and reassess. It's
pretty straightforward.
And you can use this
principle on any
area of the body
that you're treating.
So here are your take
-home points. The still
technique is a passive,
indirect, then direct
technique. It utilizes muscle
spindle and articulation
of the joint as the
physiologic mechanisms.
And basically,
you're going to guide
the dysfunction
to its freedoms,
compress,
maintain compression, and
guide it into and through
the barrier, return to baseline
position, and reassess.
Thank you and please
don't forget to
click on the lecture
feedback link at the end
of this presentation and
fill that out. Thanks.